<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!-- Copyright (c) 2006  Dustin Sallings (dustin@spy.net) -->

<document>
	<properties>
		<author email="dustin@spy.net">Dustin Sallings</author>
		<title>java memcached client</title>
	</properties>

	<body>
		<section name="Overview">
			<p>
				This is a simple, asynchronous, single-threaded memcached client
				written in java.
			</p>
			<h2>Features</h2>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<strong>Efficient storage of objects.</strong>
					General serializable objects are stored in their serialized form and
					optionally compressed if they meet criteria.  Certain native objects
					are stored as tightly as possible (for example, a Date object
					generally consumes six bytes, and a Long can be anywhere from zero to
					eight bytes).
				</li>
				<li>
					<strong>Resilient to server and network outages.</strong>
					In many cases, a client operation can be replayed against a server if
					it goes away and comes back.  In cases where it can't, it will
					communicate that as well.  An exponential backoff reconnect algorithm
					is applied when a memcached becomes unavailable, but asynchronous
					operations will queue up for the server to be applied when it comes
					back online.
				</li>
				<li>
					<strong>Operations are asynchronous.</strong>
					It is possible to issue a store and continue processing without
					having to wait for that operation to finish.  It is even possible to
					issue a get, do some further processing, check the result of the get
					and cancel it if it doesn't return fast enough.
				</li>
				<li>
					<strong>There is only one thread for all processing.</strong>
					Regardless of the number of requests, threads using the client, or
					servers to which the client is connected, only one thread will ever
					be allocated to a given MemcachedClient.
				</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section name="Where to Get">
			<h3>Binary Distributions</h3>
			<p>
				My <a href="http://bleu.west.spy.net/~dustin/repo/">maven 1
				repository</a> has the latest binary version here:
				<blockquote>
					http://bleu.west.spy.net/~dustin/repo/
				</blockquote>
			</p>
			<h3>Source Code</h3>
			<p>
				The source can be downloaded or checked out from my
				<a href="http://rubik.west.spy.net/hg/memcached/">mercurial
				repository</a>.
			</p>
			<h3>Dependencies</h3>
			<p>
				Note that this also requires
				<a href="http://bleu.west.spy.net/~dustin/projects/spyjar/">spy.jar</a>
				(2.2.44 or so) from the same repository.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="License">
			<p>
				This project is released under the
				<a href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.php">MIT</a>
				license.
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
